Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast
with the latest peer-
reviewed research
on the best ways to eat
healthy and live longer.
It’s time for the Nutrition
Facts Grab Bag,
where we look at
the latest science
on a whole variety of topics.
In our first story, we find
out if the health benefits
of peanut better
include longevity.
According to the largest study
of risk factors for death
in human history, a poor diet
causes more deaths than anything.
Cigarettes only kill about
eight million people a year,
whereas humanity’s diet
kills millions more.
What are the worst
aspects of our diet?
Processed meat? Twinkies? Soda?
No, the five deadliest
things about our diet are:
inadequate fruit intake—
not enough fruit;
not enough whole grains;
not enough vegetables;
too much salt; and not
enough nuts and seeds.
Nuts should come as no surprise
since interventional trials
have shown that eating nuts
improves artery function,
and arterial diseases
like heart disease are among
our leading killers. But
that’s not all nuts can do.
They may also improve
blood sugar control,
lower cholesterol, suppress inflammation,
reduce oxidative stress, and
feed our friendly gut flora.
All nuts or just tree nuts?
What about peanuts?
What about peanut butter?
About 50 percent of peanut
consumption in the U.S.
is through peanut butter,
but the association between
peanut butter and mortality
has not been
thoroughly evaluated. To get that
granular, though, we can call on
the NIH-AARP study, the
largest prospective health
and diet study in history
that followed more than
a half million people
since the 1990s.
And…nut consumption in
general appeared to protect
against all-cause mortality,
meaning nut-eaters live,
on average, longer lives, and
specifically, are less likely
to die from cancer, cardiovascular
disease, respiratory disease,
infectious causes (so, maybe
they help immunity as well),
liver disease, and kidney disease.
However, no such associations
were found for peanut butter.
So, when it comes to living longer,
peanut butter doesn’t
seem to count. Why?
Well, we know peanut butter
consumers tend to eat
more meat, smoke cigarettes,
and were less likely to exercise,
but the researchers
controlled for all that:
red meat, white meat, tobacco
use, exercise, and vegetables,
fruits, and whole grains;
so, it’s not like
the peanut butter eaters
were just eating more
white bread sandwiches or something.
The researchers didn’t
control for sugar though,
so it’s possible they could have
been eating more sugary jelly.
It could also be the
processing that goes into making
peanut butter—the added
transfat, oil, salt, and sugar—
but regular nuts
are also often eaten
with added oil, sugar, and salt.
Could it just be the
peanuts themselves?
Technically, they aren’t
nuts, so maybe they just
don’t have the same benefits.
But no, a meta-analysis
of all such studies found
the same nut-like benefits
for whole peanuts,
but just not peanut butter.
Well, one thing missing
from even no salt, oil-free,
sugar-free nut and seed butters
is intact cellular structure.
As I noted in How Not to Diet,
no matter how well we chew
whole or chopped nuts, some
of the nutrients remain trapped
in tiny particles that
deliver a bounty of
prebiotic goodness to
our friendly flora.
That makes me wonder if there
would have been any difference
between chunky and
smooth peanut butter.
In the meanwhile there is
compelling evidence to recommend
the use of nuts (preferably raw
nuts over salted or toasted)
and whole or chopped nuts
rather than nut butters,
at least three times a
week in order to maximize
your chances of living
longer and healthier lives.
In our next story, we look
at what physicians can do
to promote healthy,
life-extending,
lifestyle changes.
A pivotal paper published in
Europe more than a decade ago
entitled “Healthy Living Is
the Best Revenge” found that
adhering to just four simple
healthy lifestyle factors
compared to none could
potentially have a strong impact
on the prevention
of chronic diseases;
we’re talking nearly 80 percent
less chronic disease risk,
slashing diabetes
risk by 93 percent,
dropping heart attack
risk by 81 percent,
and cutting stroke risk in half,
and cancer by 36 percent.
Think about what that means.
The potential for preventing
disease and death is enormous.
In the U.S. alone every year,
there are half a million
heart attacks, half a million
strokes, a million new cases
of diabetes, and a
million new cancer diagnoses.
The message is clear:
adopting a few healthy behaviors
can have a major impact.
What are those four fabled factors?
Never smoking, not being obese,
averaging about a half hour of
exercise a day, and adhering to
healthy dietary principles,
like lots of fruits, vegetables,
and whole grains, and less meat.
Follow those four
simple rules and boom!
Enjoy nearly 80 percent reduced
risk of major chronic diseases.
What does that mean
for mortality risk?
A similar batch of four healthy
behaviors combined predicted
a four-fold difference
in total mortality,
with an estimated impact
equivalent to 14 years
in chronological age, meaning
the individuals were dying at
such a reduced rate that it was
as if they were 14 years younger.
“Finally, a Regimen to
Extend Human Life Expectancy.”
This commentary was in
reference to this study,
where a similar analysis
of the impact of healthy
lifestyle behaviors on
life expectancies was made,
but this time it looked
directly at the U.S. population,
which is particularly important,
since Americans have a
shorter life expectancy
compared with residents
of nearly all other
high-income countries.
The researchers concluded that
adopting a healthy lifestyle
could substantially
reduce premature mortality
and prolong life
expectancy in U.S. adults.
Okay, but by how much?
They estimated that adherence
to a low-risk lifestyle
could prolong life expectancy
at age 50 by 14 years
in women and 12.2 years in men.
So, if you’re 50 right now,
instead of only living to 79
if you’re a woman, and
75½ if you’re a man,
taking even just basic care
of yourself could propel you
to an average life expectancy
of 93 if you’re a woman
and 87½ if you’re a man.
The bottom line is it’s never
too late to turn back the clock.
A midlife switch just
to the basics, like at least
five servings fruits
and vegetables a day,
walking even like 20 minutes a day,
maintaining a healthy
weight, and not smoking
results in a substantial
reduction in mortality
even in the following few years.
We’re talking a 40 percent
lower risk of dying
in the subsequent four years.
So, making the necessary
changes to adhere to a healthy
lifestyle could be considered
extremely worthwhile,
and middle age is certainly
not too late to act.
As an aside, realizing the
12 to 14 years of added life
study was based on data
from health professionals,
that got me excited about
all the potential knock-on effects.
If health professionals
start getting healthier,
they could become role models
for more healthful living
and potentially save more
lives than just their own.
But that may have just
been wishful thinking.
Practicing what you preach
can sometimes backfire.
Evidently, “displays of excellence
can paradoxically turn off
the very people they
are trying to inspire.”
You’d assume that not
being a hypocrite and trying
to walk the walk would just
lead to positive consequences,
inspiring confidence in others, right?
Don’t you want a dance instructor
who can dance, a music teacher
who can play, a health
professional who’s healthy?
But this simple intuition
fails to take into account
concerns about making
other people feel inadequate.
Like you know how vegetarians
are the targets of a
surprising amount of
hostility and ridicule.
That’s because they may
come off as morally superior
and make people feel like
they’re being looked down upon.
There was an elegant
demonstration of this phenomenon
in this study where
“Principled deviants who take
the high road threaten
others’ moral self-worth.”
This is what they did.
Research subjects were asked
to complete a racist
task by an experimenter,
and those moral rebels who
refused to obey were cheered
by observers but were
disparaged by participants
who had themselves
gone through with it,
and for whom the rebel’s stance
thus implied an indictment
of their spinelessness.
Isn’t that interesting?
So, when doctors portray themselves
as “the picture of health,”
patients might think they’re
being holier-than-thou and
unintentionally alienate people,
potentially turning off
the very patients who
most need their help.
You can see how someone with
a weight issue might feel
threatened and judged
by a physician triathlete.
But what are we supposed to do?
We want healthy practitioners.
Physicians who
smoke are less likely
to tell their patients
to quit smoking,
physicians who are overweight
are less likely to counsel
their patients about weight,
and physicians
who don’t work out
are less likely to
talk about exercise.
What we can do to make
patients more comfortable
is emphasize that our
role is to help people
meet their own personal health
goals, whatever they may be.
Studies show that when doctors
do this, take this approach,
it increases the appeal of
fitness-focused physicians
to overweight patients.
So, we can then display
exemplary behavior
while at the same time
not inadvertently alienate
the very people who could
benefit most from our guidance.
Finally today, we look at
cancer-causing contaminants
in medication and meat.
In 2018, one of the bestselling
blood pressure drugs,
valsartan—sold as Diovan—was
found to be contaminated
by the “probably carcinogenic”
nitrosamine known as
N-nitrosodimethylamine (NDMA).
It’s believed that approximately
20 million people worldwide
were prescribed the drug
tainted with this contaminant
whose cancer risk has been shown
to exceed that of many known
potent carcinogens, including
asbestos, benzo[a]pyrene, and PCBs.
The U.S. Food and Drug Administration
(FDA) estimated that
taking the drug for a few years
could cause cancer in as many as
1 in 8,000 people, whereas the
European equivalent of the FDA
estimated the cancer risk
could be as high as 1 in 5,000.
It is unlikely, researchers
wrote in this Spring 2019 paper,
that drugs like valsartan
are a unique case.
And indeed, a few months
later, the FDA announced
it had found NDMA in ranitidine.
Ranitidine, the acid
reflux drug sold as Zantac,
is one of the most prescribed
drugs on the planet,
in addition to being
sold over the counter.
Give people a single tablet
and the amount of NDMA flowing
through their bodies jumps up
more than a hundred-fold.
Then in 2020, some formulations
of metformin, a popular diabetes drug
sold as Glucophage, were
found to be contaminated.
The finding of NDMA in common
medicines led the FDA to call for
the immediate withdrawal of
all Zantac from store shelves,
yanking the drug from the
market because their testing
showed NDMA levels could in
some circumstances exceed
the acceptable daily intake
limit of 96 nanograms per day.
It was so bad that the FDA
found levels of this carcinogenic
contaminant NDMA in Zantac similar
to the levels you would expect
to be exposed to if you ate grilled
or smoked meats! Wait, what?
NDMA has not only been found
in contaminating drugs.
It is a known byproduct of
pesticide manufacturing,
leather tanning, and tire plants,
and is found in multiple
foods and beverages, including
processed meat and beer.
Now that we know NDMA can
transfer through the placenta,
this may explain the relationship
between maternal cured meat
consumption during pregnancy and
the risk of childhood brain tumors.
For example, hot dog consumption
during pregnancy may increase
childhood brain tumor
risk by 33 percent
or sausage consumption by 44 percent.
Bacon consumption may increase
childhood brain tumor odds
by 60 or 70 percent.
But it’s not just processed meat.
Researchers have found it
in poultry products as well.
A single serving of chicken contains
more than 100 nanograms of NDMA.
Remember how the FDA said
the acceptable daily intake limit
is 96 nanograms per day?
Half of a chicken
breast contains
110.
Now, raw poultry doesn’t have any;
it’s the cooking process.
In fact, the dry-heat cooking of
meat, like broiling or grilling,
even creates airborne NDMA,
releasing this very potent
carcinogenic compound into the air.
So, even if you’re only
getting a salad or something in a
charcoal grill restaurant, just
being indoors where meat
is being cooked could pose
a signiﬁcant cancer risk.
These nitrosamines are also
found in cigarette smoke,
and pressure was put on the tobacco
industry to try to remove them,
arguing that there is simply no
logical reason why a removable
carcinogen should be allowed
to remain in a consumer product.
That’s the same reason Zantac
was yanked from store shelves.
Okay, so let me get this straight.
One of the best-selling drugs inhistory
was pulled from the market—
a drug that brought in billions of dollars—
because it contained a probable
carcinogen that exceeded
the acceptable daily limit,
but there may be more
of the contaminant in a
single serving of chicken!
So, my question is:
why aren’t they pulling the
poultry off the shelves as well?
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.